so you've been saying many times
that the problem
is that we are affected
in the first place in other words we are
we anger is possible lust is possible
we get we can get confused suffering is
possible suffering
is possible for us
could you so the goal really is to
not be affected in the first place
not to do something on a counter yeah
well the like that's the kind of
fundamental difference that i often try to highlight
difference that i often try to highlight
is dharma the practice of dhamma
is not supposed to just help you with
things help you with things that bother you
help you with things that bother you
help you deal with them
it's basically supposed to uproot
your liability to it to things the body
so it doesn't manage your suffering it
removes possibility for you to suffer
in the first place
so you and that's that is a personal
goal for your practice
it should be i
don't want to be affected by things to
begin with
not i want to have a perfect management
technique that will always help me deal with
that will always help me deal with
whatever suffering have arisen
see that's the problem already suffering
hazarism you might be very skilled in dealing
you might be very skilled in dealing
with it but you're not skilled in not
having it arise in the first place
and that's what should be your issue so
that's why even you know
the buddha would often describe like his
teaching that frees you from suffering brings
that frees you from suffering brings
cessation of being
the the ending of bhava the ending of
these things becoming for you
manifesting enduring that you have to
manage them then later
means they're not anymore being deceased
they're gone
so that is the goal of the dhamma
cessation of being not management of
things that are for you
here and now cessation of
suffering cessation of greed diversion
delusion
so i i can get angry
i can get angry but then i can find out
a
some sort of technique to manage my
anger yeah oh when you
get angry think these thoughts when
you're angry do this
when i only do that that's how you start
you need to be
well you need to want to be free from
anger to begin with
and then inevitably your first
effort will be directed at how to manage
and subdue the anger
but you mustn't confuse that for the
actual practice of the dhamma
which if done rightly will uproot the
anger and then there's nothing for you to
and then there's nothing for you to
manage no burden for you to have to do
or deal with
and if you don't do it you will then
suffer no there is nothing to be
dealt with because nothing affects you
to begin with
you say it's not the dumber that
management is not the dhamma
exactly it's like the approximation of
the dharma but it's not it's not that
it's not the direct way
one way only the way the buddha would
describe the dhamma would always only
result in purification of being like
like removing all the unwholesomeness and
removing all the unwholesomeness and
making bhava cease
management doesn't do that only that
direct insight into what
it what uproots suffering what is
uprooting the greed
what is uprooting the aversion and
delusion
so the dump what so what is the dumbbell
what is that is a direct path
to for uprooting not the management
so you are kind of responsible for
whether things you're doing
whether you've taken them as dhamma
whether you're taking them for the
purpose of uprooting the
issues not dealing with it but like
making yourself
not liable to them even in the future
or have you taken the dumb instruction
as me
as a means sort of of helping yourself
deal with these things
so it's more like it's it's it's more
it's determined by you by your attitude
determined by you by your attitude
whether that instruction
will be taken as the dhamma or as
management
that's the that's the difference i'm
pointing at you know like you can do
sati patana which is the dhamma the
the the way the word described but you
can do it for the reasons of managing
your suffering not for the reasons of
approaching it
which means you are responsible for
whether it's management or it's the
dhamma and yeah that's why the dumb arises in
and yeah that's why the dumb arises in
those who see
you know i can like you can tell the
dharma directly the buddha would teach
them to somebody but he wouldn't be the
to somebody but he wouldn't be the
dumber for them because they're not
understanding it so there is no rising
of dharma in their experience
but he is the thing they would have said
but they are not understanding it
so the dhamma can only arise on that
individual level the dhamma the way
knowing the the knowledge of the way the
knowledge of the way of uprooting things
basically that's what it is
the knowledge of of overcoming liability
to suffering once and for all not just
the knowledge of how to manage it
skillfully when it arises
so you can look and see
i am subject to suffering
i will things can go wrong well exactly
it's it's it's really on that level of i
will i will experience this i am liable
to this
that's we often say that that's why we
said the wise men who reflect the young
man who leaves the home
i am pray to suffering not necessarily
suffering now
but the suffering will catch me at some
point it's it's inevitable
and you should stop you should have the
like mental basically clarity enough
mental capacity sufficiently enough to
start seeing
that as the actual root of the problem
not the fact that you might they're like
oh i suffer now i don't suffer tomorrow
or whatever that i will at some point
it's inevitable and that's the true
problem even if i spend the rest of my
life skillfully avoiding all the major
suffering the fact is it will still have to i am
the fact is it will still have to i am
still liable
to it i still have to make the effort to
avoid it
that's already the issue the divine
messenger you know the buddha was
neither sick
nor old nor dying when he saw a sick
aging dead person so you see that
dead person so you see that
ah this is directly present in my
experience as the inherent liability and that's
as the inherent liability and that's
what the issue is
and that's why this is the difference in
in practice
of management and the practice of
uprooting let's call it that way
it's basically in recognizing like okay
so there is no lust in my experience
here and now
there is no greed in my experience here
and now there is no delusion
experience here okay i'm fine then no
but now as the buddha would say
okay so in you ask yourself further it's
good that those things are not present
here and now
but your next question should now be
so is it possible for non-reason
lust to arise later on now it's not here
but can it be here tomorrow
oh have i addressed that here and now
not wait for tomorrow to address it
and that's literally the crossroads
between are you heading in the direction of
are you heading in the direction of
uprooting it or are you heading
directional management
and most people go down the path of
management as in i'll deal with it when
it arises
failing to understand that liability to
future lust
is a risen issue now
you don't have to wait for it to rise is
there a chance for non-manifested lust
non-manifested aversion to manifest in
my experience
later if you're not sure means that is a
chance if you know for sure there you go you
if you know for sure there you go you
confirmed it so there is a chance that
these things will arise
that's the issue for me now when those
things are not present
yeah anger is a problem possibility
for anger is a problem yeah now no not
uh
not in the future it is now a problem
and that's that's the whole that's like
the what differentiates your practice
from are you
aiming at the uprooting or are you just
aiming at the skillful management
and you heard that yourself before it's
it's very common attitude of
oh well you know most of the time you
are not lustful
most of the time you're not angry so see
you're doing fine
if most of the time you're not angry
means anger is still
your liability your possibility which
means you're as angry
like yeah you're not acting out of that
anger as often as others but that's just
because you learn some management
of your anger you're certainly not
uprooting anything if you have the
attitude that
most of the time these things don't
arise for me
yeah but could they arise at any time
yes that's the issue you're not seeing and
that's the issue you're not seeing and
that's why you're not approaching
anything
so so you see that there is a problem
because you
see and know that there is the
possibility yeah
of angus so you have to train your mind
to start seeing these possibilities
as actually present because they are so
you can think to yourself
i can manage my lust or my anger
quite well i am i'm really skilled at
that i know all these different techniques
i know all these different techniques
psychological methods
to employ yeah so that i can ease that
anger ease that lust and be calm again if if
ease that lust and be calm again if if
your way out of suffering
is skillful managing it you need
suffering to arise first
so management requires suffering in
order to manage it
so management cannot free you from that
suffering it can only deal with it once it has
it can only deal with it once it has
arisen
and most people that's that's the kind
of problem that's sort of
relatively subtle i suppose is people
as i said natural tendencies to turn
towards management first
oh they can get rid of the problem do it
skillfully whatever else
um but there is this kind of conflating
that occurs then
or rather confusion so through your
management of suffering
you experience like less duka
and and then at the same time you kind
of start
basically tacitly assuming um hoping
that all you have to do is manage your
suffering long enough
and then somehow magically liability to
duke will disappear
so all i have to do is is adhere to this
management and skillful avoiding and so
on
and there's already implicit as i said
wishful thinking
that implies that you hopeful suffering
will then just
poof eventually from your management it
will just evaporate
but it won't that's the point the only
way that suffering will evaporate is if
you evaporate it if you understand the core
evaporate it if you understand the core
pull
the thorn out
it won't come out by itself so uproot it
so if you keep managing it with a hope
that somehow it will disappear
on the level of that i am still liable
to it
means your practice revolves around
wishful thinking there is no direct
insight this is what to be done for freedom from
this is what to be done for freedom from
suffering because yeah you don't want
eventually everyone's goal is to not
have exactly
everybody everybody wants to to be fully
free from suffering which means
everybody wants to not
even be liable to discomfort and
displeasure so i start doing meta metamata meta meta
so i start doing meta metamata meta meta
every day every day every day
and i stay calm i don't get angry
but i have to keep doing math as well as
i can so your kindness then is dependent
upon the factor of you sustaining your
effort towards
whatever you perceive matter
contemplation to be which means if
sometimes circumstances change you get
sick or something happens or too many
things happen you don't have enough time
so you cannot engage to that necessary
extent of your
of your of your meta contemplation means
you're back
back within anger so you haven't really
uprooted anger
you just suppressed it with a certain
practices and as i said there is nothing is not
and as i said there is nothing is not
it's not inherently wrong
to do that to begin with but it's
inherently wrong to adopt a view that
doing that
uproots things somehow magically the
only way to approach
things is to directly see what uprooting
is
and i just described it what it is it's
recognizing that liability
the possibility of anger possibility of
ill will
possibility of sensuality possibility of
delusion possibility of dukkha as the
dukkha right now not to wait for it
when it occurs so you see that possibly
see the possibility
so what do you do how do you uproot this
possibility that tomorrow you might suffer you're
that tomorrow you might suffer you're
being aware of that then then
then then
well it's sustaining that so can you
sustain that if if you're not keeping
the precepts can you sustain that
elevated state of mind
that recognizes liability to dukkha
without the actual dukkha being present
there if you're drinking smoking running
if you're drinking smoking running
around distracting yourself
engaging in entertainment no impossible
so that the noble aid for path that's
how you do it right livelihood
right view first first of all see if
your view
still regards management
as the way out of suffering you will not
stay on the level of weight
is the possibility of suffering that's
the problem they must be dealt with
not the actual suffering rain arises
so again how do i deal with that how do
you deal with what the possibility
but nobody for part yeah so right right
view knowing that that's where the issue is
knowing that that's where the issue is
not looking elsewhere
right intentions uh not entertaining not
delighting not giving in to agree
diversion delusion through your speech
through your body in your thoughts
so on every front you need to build
yourself up in order to be able to
sustain that recognition of liability here and
that recognition of liability here and
now it's what the issue is
if you ask yourself how do i deal with
the possibility
of future suffering here and now you're
basically asking how to manage it
how do i manage this possibly well
that's what you're implying because you
want to deal with it
now you deal with it properly not not
give in to the view of management
by realizing that you have no right to
resist it
so you have to be careful if you when
you start recognizing ah the liability
of suffering is the problem for me
you have to be careful to now not give
in to the attitude of wanting to manage
that so i want it
so i want it
to end i want that possibility
to be gone so then you really have to
understand where the dukkha is there is the
where the dukkha is there is the
possibility in itself dukkha
is that possibility of future discomfort
future disagreeable things is that in itself
disagreeable things is that in itself
the idea yeah the thought of it is it is
it is that the dukkha
no so i would say so what's the dukkha
then i would say it's that unpleasant feeling
i would say it's that unpleasant feeling
it's the
this pleasure that is that is there
when i have that idea right
so i feel uncomfortable the fact that
in the future i will
suffer pain which i'm suffering
presently because of that it might be so then the
because of that it might be so then the
next question you should ask yourself
is the uh so the unpleasant feeling then
that you have when you think those
thoughts is that a duke in itself
because it is what it is that pain
well yeah the problem is i don't want it
there so so what is then the dukkha
i mean i would say okay it's the craving
to get rid of it
okay so how's that manifested what is
that practically in your experience
resistance so yeah i resist so that's
for me that sense of entitled of i
i i should not have this so you realize
you suffer because you resist the
discomfort even before the discomfort comes your
even before the discomfort comes your
way see you resist
the thought of the possibility of
discomfort here and now
and that's why here and now you
experience dukkha
that's why the buddha didn't say vedana
is the cause of dukkha he didn't say
feelings are the cause of suffering he
said tanha
craving is the cause of suffering
craving in regard to what you feel
so you have such and such feeling when
you have such and such thought
present future or past but it's your
implicit attitude towards the feeling of either
attitude towards the feeling of either
craving towards it or away from it
that's why that experience is dukkha and
see you would have not seen that if you
you would have not seen that if you
haven't forced yourself
to discern the level of that possibility
of dukkha
is dukkha right now you wouldn't have
seen that if you were just
fully bent managing the dukkha as it
arises or managing the dukkha before it arrives
or managing the dukkha before it arrives
specific pain
yes so that's what i mean like even the
even when people recognize sometimes the
future duke reliability to the future
dukkha they can they can even take that as
they can they can even take that as
something to manage
ah so i'll do this i'll do this so these
things will not happen to me
which carries the implicit view that
dukkha is
in those actual things or in your actual
feelings and you don't see that it's in your
and you don't see that it's in your
attitude towards these things
and yeah it's right now right here right
now always present
exactly experiencing that pressure the
relationship between tanha
and between craving and suffering it's
always present
always simultaneously present presence
of suffering presence of suffering
means presence of tanha presence of
tanha means presence of suffering so to the
means presence of suffering so to the
extent that tanha is
present to that extent suffering is felt
or to the extent the suffering is felt
to that extent attitude of tanhai is
present there is no delay or like few seconds
there is no delay or like few seconds
later dukkha comes as a result of your
craving the presence of suffering means presence
the presence of suffering means presence
of craving
presence of craving means presence of
suffering so that's why if you were to
remove the presence of craving
there is no suffering amidst things that
used to cause you to suffer so much
and that's where liberation is visible
and possible from suffering
here and now so that's what i mean you
need to start seeing
as duca the liability to suffering
not actually wait for the actual
suffering and then manage it
because if you don't see that liability
then you're
complacent if you're not seeing the
liability means you're not seeing where your
means you're not seeing where your
craving is well you're not seeing dukkha
you're not saying yeah you need to see
the dukkha first
in order to see the cause of dukkha you
can't just be dealing with the dukkha
without understanding what dukkha is
that's what i said i am teaching suffering and
what i said i am teaching suffering and
i'm teaching freedom
i teach only two things suffering and
freedom from it that's it
so if you don't see that possibility of
future discomfort is already dukkha now
means you're not seeing the nature of
dukkha to begin with
so doesn't matter what happens to you
you will not see it with the correct
set of eyes so to speak
and if you're not seeing what the dukkha
is here and now
already you're not going to see a
craving because as i said to the extent that the
because as i said to the extent that the
duke has felt to that extent craving is
present but you're not seeing the felt dukkha
but you're not seeing the felt dukkha
that's how can you see that which which
determines it
the actual craving so that's what i mean
management looking to deal with it over there
looking to deal with it over there
without seeing where the actual dooka
is because you give in to that need to
manage it and remove the pain as opposed
to understand it
it's it's inherently bound in the wrong
view it's inherently bound in the wrong
direction there's just like a way you could
there's just like a way you could
reflect why are you entitled
to to to manage pain have you had saying
it's a
like dwell on the nature of that dukkha
even the actual do code the future duke
just just reflecting
have you had say in its arising can you
prevent circumstances from becoming disagreeable
circumstances from becoming disagreeable
at any point in the future is that even
conceivable actually it's just a pure fantasy
actually it's just a pure fantasy
fantasy rooted in this complete
misconceiving of the problem problem is in these
of the problem problem is in these
things happening to me
problem is not in me implicitly
resisting the idea of these things happening to me
the idea of these things happening to me
so how do you stop resisting
the pain how do you then stop
craving or rather welcoming the pleasure
how do you remove craving
well we just outlined it but not trying
to manage it
but by seeing it here and now already
and then by sense restraint because you
cannot possibly be welcoming pleasure
and then just dealing with the
unpleasant uh experiences when they
arise you can't just selectively pick
and choose which cravings you want
if there is any form of craving present
means liability to suffering is present
so you have to abandon craving for
pleasure in as much you have to abandon
craving against pain
yeah so pain comes pleasure comes you
have no saying it's arising
so why do you then constantly um
entertain the attitude of i want this i
don't want this
i have right to want this i have right
to not want this
why do you go after one try to avoid the
other one
where is your attitude rooted why are
you doing it
because that's because pleasure and pain
is yeah it's felt
it's a pressure it pressures you you
feel so it's painful to not do it yeah so you
so it's painful to not do it yeah so you
do it because you want to avoid pain
because it's pressure the pain is pain
is pressuring so exactly so you don't
know how to deal with duka
thus you try to get rid of duka that's
basically the
the the nutshell of every management
and that's what say it's inherently
wrong even if you're doing the dhamma
all the buddha's instruction but you're
taking them as management
means you still entertain the same
attitude because of which you suffer in
the first place
which is i can handle this i want to get
rid of it which is the attitude of
craving
so how can you then withstand the
pressure how can you withstand the pressure
how can you withstand the pressure
that's amazing
by withstanding the pressure can you
withstand the pressure if even your
physical behavior is not kept in check
can you withstand mental pressure then
impossible if your verbal behavior is not kept in
if your verbal behavior is not kept in
check
like the outpost of lust and anger
through your physical action through
your verbal action
if you don't keep a lid on that can you
possibly withstand things mentally not a
chance and how do you do that by doing it like
and how do you do that by doing it like
how do you become stronger
well by exposing yourself to things that
will make you stronger by training
i said that many times like even when i
first read those suddens i was a bit
puzzled but with
keeps kept talking about he trains
himself thus
a monk skill monk trains himself thus
because you know you had all these
notions about enlightenment and
someone's like what is there to train
you know you do things and then
enlightenment happens to you no
you train the strength out of which
wisdom comes which is what enlightenment
is
so that's a sense restraint is not
optional that's what
virtue is not you know oh i can do it
for a while
it's a necessary basis that has to
remain throughout
so you will be able to withstand the
pressure by not giving into pressure
by not giving into pressure you get to
outline what the actual problem is
your liability to future pressure to
future discomfort
is already the problem right here right
now and you see that now because you haven't
and you see that now because you haven't
just blindly gave in
to managing of the pressure in order to
get rid of the pressure
manage the stress in order to get rid of
the stress practice the dharma
so you don't get this particular stress
anymore i recognize it is a possibility of
i recognize it is a possibility of
suffering
and i see that suffering right now
it's suffering because i resist the
displeasure here and now
in regard to the possibility
it's suffering because i resist
so i don't resist it
that discomfort here and now
but i must have that i must still have
the idea that
i don't have to keep on thinking about
that there's a possibility of me
suffering tomorrow
no they will come and go
so whatever basically i have to look at
whatever i'm feeling right now yeah
yeah because that's where the resistance
occurs that's what craving is
it's where you feel yeah i can put the
the possibility of something i put that
aside because now i know what the
problem is here and now
sure sure so i've i've come today you
contemplate the possibility of suffering
when you forget what the problem is here
and now
or where you're not seeing it well you
could yeah like sariputta just
ask himself i think it was
what am i liable to anything to any
suffering is it some of that
yeah it was something that is suffering
that can arise yeah is there any any
suffering that hasn't
that the possibility of suffering hasn't
been like addressed so to speak
yeah i was like no i don't see any
okay he still doesn't decide okay i'm
done now
no you remain with that vigilant
attitude you've done this okay i'll check i'll
you've done this okay i'll check i'll
check in every now and then and see if
something has changed
if possibility for lust aversion
delusion possibility for pressure
possibility for central pull possibility
for suffering
has that arisen now not the actual
suffering but
the possibility for it being oh look
yeah now i see it yeah it could be
possible there you go that's your issue right
there you go that's your issue right
there and then so what you do
well you don't lose the sight of it to
begin with that feeling
yeah you don't welcome it if it's the
possibility that it's pleasure and
sensuality and you don't resist it if it's the
and you don't resist it if it's the
possibility to it's pain and discomfort
is there anything that is there a
possibility for me
uh indulging in welcoming doubting is
too close already it's the result of
pleasure in the future
exactly so it's on the level of the
possibility of pleasure or possibility
of pain which means on the level of
welcoming or kind of shying away from
it's suffering same thing if someone
brings me a pizza tomorrow i love the
taste of pizza will i
when i welcome that pleasure pleasurable
taste will i get
lost you will know that if you're
looking at things rightly you will know
that already now
you'll know oh no i can't wait even if
you are perfectly restrained and don't
express your joy over the particular type of
your joy over the particular type of
food brought to you
you already internally you know what it
what it is and so that
and that's the problem but there's the
work and that's the work
exactly that's where the issue is
and people would okay so i will tell
them never to bring that thing again
because i like it too much
it's like well you can do that as a way
of like if you really can't deal with
things so okay put it aside but
that's really masking the issue the
issue is not
the pizza whatever people have brought
to you the issue is you're unable to
restrain yourself
you're unable to have mind free from
greed so now you're just trying to remove
so now you're just trying to remove
things that make you greedy but
you're able to not be
wanting pleasure you are unable to
exactly to to to not
welcome that pressure of that pleasure
you're unable which means that's why you
will remain liable you can spend 100
years of that management you will never
approve to your sensuality
so you feel the pressure of pain that
resistance against it
and you stop well exactly you don't try
to get rid of it
you don't try to psychologize manage
explain prevent things from arising obviously if
prevent things from arising obviously if
something obviously unwholesome
like like like when that man came and
offered wanted to offer his daughter to the
wanted to offer his daughter to the
buddha and he said no don't even bother
i will not accept that
like certain things cannot be done
rightly such as sexual intercourse and
and so on
but there are things that there's
nothing like there's nothing wrong in
eating food whether it's tasty or not
but it's wrong in eating it with sensual
reasons and you eat
when you eat you eat your food with
sensual reasons when
when you are unable to to not be
overwhelmed by that uh pressure towards accepting
by that uh pressure towards accepting
pleasure
so that's what we would say like when
you when you practice in regard to the
food you know like you stop eating no you eat
you know like you stop eating no you eat
mindfully
you maintain the reasons for your eating
clearly and you eat what those reasons
are present
reasons for health sustaining the body
so that you can practice further not the
reasons of
beautifications chasing the taste and so
on
but if you just think if i avoid the
food i don't have to deal with these
reasons well you're sorely mistaken you're just
well you're sorely mistaken you're just
covering up the basis of your sensuality
so even if you just eat horrible stuff
all the time because you don't want to
experience any
sensual joy of the taste you still need
to look at these reasons and keep the
vigilant eye on them because that's
where sensuality is rooted
not in the actual taste
so am i welcoming am i delighting am i
accepting this elation on account of
central prospect that is pleasing to me
that's the issue my
acceptance not seeing the danger in it
not just to maintain
not that's the issue not the issue is oh
i must not have this thing
arise for me at all so
call people tell them never to bring
their food never to you'll never see
anything you'll never hear anything
you'll never taste anything agreeable
and you you're not you're misconceiving
where the issue is
yeah and you're maintaining the issue
well you remain fully within it yeah
that's why you you're not you're not
stepping outside of central domains
there might be someone that comes along
and that's why the asceticism you know
the atmos form like you know
giants you know the the perfect practice
of of obsessive
hingsa non-violence and not eating not
harming anything it's artem is guided
because it's fully misprojected they
don't see where the issue really is
you know avoiding food any and if you're
just eating every third day or something
to the point of in the end
you die on a kind of starvation and
that's like the ultimate goal of a giant
yet you realize you fully remained bound
by the central domain
never a step closer to escape it because
the jains it's
said that by avoiding
things then you you you diminish
them yeah diminish the pressure but
whereas the buddhist way is what because
it's not always the same things
you don't always have one attitude
towards all things if you were to only
have the attitude of accepting
everything every type of feeling every type of
every type of feeling every type of
perception then giants would have been
right all you need to do is avoid it because
all you need to do is avoid it because
you always accept it but but that's not
the case
you're not you're not accepting the
unpleasurable feelings
you are actually trying to get rid of
them you're only accepting certain
things but then you're resisting some other
but then you're resisting some other
things
and so it's not a blanket rule always
avoid because
it's not a blanket experience that's
always the same
that's why what you do whether you avoid
or whether you have to basically endure
is determined by
how you feel and you don't even feel
that always the same in regard to the
same things
sometimes one same food might make you
happy sometimes might make you
unpleasant sometimes might might make you
sometimes might might make you
indifferent
which means you have three different
types of foods you can have three
different types of attitude
that will then exhibit the craving but
if you always avoid everything
you're ignoring two-thirds of that
picture and that's why you will remain
ignorant so how can you then know when to reject
so how can you then know when to reject
and when to accept
like when you're resisting gratuitously
the future prospect of suffering
should you be rejecting that even more
no you need to accept that these
possibilities are there present and you
have no say in it
that's how you can then stop resisting
it gratuitously
and thus you approve the suffering
or should you then accept the the
prospect of future pleasure that you
already delight in it no you must reject
that you must contemplate the danger in
it
so how do you know what you do well by
learning how to be properly mindful of
an enduring feeling
because that's where things converge
that's where things are rooted
you can't just take a set of behavior
that you always do this when it's this
and this when it's that no
first you just need to remain mindful of
what's the present enduring feeling
and you will know then what attitude is
there if the pleasant enduring feeling is of
if the pleasant enduring feeling is of
pleasure and agreeability
means you have the attitude of welcoming
it by default but you must
so that's that's what you reject you
reject your welcoming
of this central pleasure you don't blame
like giants the actual object of your
central pleasure
so you will know what attitude is there
by correctly understanding what present
feeling is there
that's the root of the problem is the
it's always present
the root of the problem is always
present it's not in the past it will not
be in the future that's the root of the
problem exactly and the root of that present
exactly and the root of that present
root is basically your attitude towards
the present
enduring feeling so it's whatever
suffering will arise in the future or is
that's the gateway it's within that that
doesn't disappear when the suffering
arrives that remains its vessel
so to speak its framework as i say
because no amount of future discomfort
and suffering can affect you
unless you're holding on to that vessel
of rejecting it
like the vessel of rejection basically
of any discomfort that's your mindset
so anything that comes of this
comfortable nature is going to make you
suffer because of your attitude of not
wanting it
you remove the attitude of that
kirchhoff that you're not wanting the
discomfort not necessarily seeking it out but
not necessarily seeking it out but
certainly not trying to get rid of it
when it when it's there exactly when it
circumstances arise which inevitably
will ah then you are not cultivating that
ah then you are not cultivating that
gratuitous mindset
of resistance which means your craving
is now truly diminishing
and same you will diminish your craving
when you don't cultivate gratuitous
mindset of welcoming as they would say
delighting entertaining
the notions of current and future
pleasure like why are you like when you ask
like why are you like when you ask
yourself am i liable to future essential
desire oh yes why because here and now
oh yes why because here and now
i'm still holding it there i'm still
welcoming the prospect of it
here and now i haven't uprooted it not i
haven't dealt with it rightly
once it has arisen no it's on the level
of
that possible future sensuality is only
possible because right here right now i am still
because right here right now i am still
valuing it i'm still haven't seen the
thought of danger in it i'm still on
some level delighting in it
and that delight is to be dealt with
here and now
not in the future when that thing arises